John M. Budarz Papers 1948-1989 CPAA 95-12
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
John M. Budarz Papers
1948-1996
John M. Budarz
CPAA 95-12
2 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
John M. Budarz was one of the founders of the Polish Art League of Pittsburgh and held the presidency of the organization twice. Mr. Budarz was also active in the American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs, an umbrella organization for various cultural clubs on the national level. Material in this collection relates to activities of Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh, information on numerous cultural events, correspondence, and includes publication of their newsletter - Palette.
Biographical Note
John M. Budarz, 1906-1994, born in Windsor, Conn., graduate of Norwich University in Vermont and the Law School of Duquesne University in Pittsburgh. Mr. Budarz was one of the founding members, long time officer, treasurer and twice president of the Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh. He worked in the insurance business and the Consulate of the Republic of Poland (1921-1945). He was active in the American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs, serving as a vice-president, treasurer and chairman of several committees.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh was created in 1948 to promote Polish Culture and tradition and to support Polish and American authors, artists, and performers. It is an affiliate of the American Council of Polish Culture (formerly American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs) and twice was a host of its national convention. Over the years it organized numerous concerts, lectures, performances, exhibitions, festivals, etc. It established special scholarship, published monthly newsletter called Palette, conducted educational campaigns, and cooperated with various Polish American organizations. It regularly brought shows from Poland. Twice, in 1953 and 1988 it organized the presentation of Moniszko's opera "Halka". This collection consists of correspondence, reports, announcements, financial records, constitutions and by-laws, membership lists, newsletter, newspaper clippings, and pamphlets covering the years 1948-1989.
The collection is open for research.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Ms. Camille Budarz, a daughter of Mr. John M. Budarz in 1995.
Search Terms
Budarz, John M.; Budarz, Camille A.; Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh; Polish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh.; Polish Americans -- Societies, etc.; American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs -- History.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Programs.; Musical notes.
Related Material
For related material from Connecticut Polish American Archives see the following collections:
Amarican Council for Polish Culture records CPAA 96-03
Joseph L. Zazyczny collection of American Council of Polish Culture records CPAA 99-15
Alfred F. Bochenek collection of American Council of Polish Culture records CPAA 02-01
Arrangement
Mr. Alfred Bochenek kept the ACPCC files in a chronological order and the original arrangement is kept within the collection.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- John M. Budarz - biography and obituary., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh - Constitution., June 1939, 1952, 1956, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh - Reports., 1949-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh - correspondence., 1949-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3A)
- Polish Arts League - Committees., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh - programs., 1951-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Polish Arts League - press releases., 1950's-1960's (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh - Membership 1975 - 1978. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh - minutes, correspondence, notes., 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7A)
- Polish Arts League - Newsletter., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Polish Arts League - clippings., 1950's (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Polish Arts League - 40th anniversary luncheon, related correspondence., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Polish Arts League - Survey., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- PALETTE - official publication of the Polish Arts League of Pittsburgh (scattered issues)., 1950-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Polish Arts Club of Buffalo, Inc. Monthly Bulletin., October 1979-January 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12A)
- Joseph Pilato (actor) - application for grant to travel to Poland., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Tadeusz Kerner Concert program, guest list, related correspondence., August 6, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Piotr Janowski Concert, program and related correspondence., April 14, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Polish Musical Show - Parade of Polish Stars., October 2, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bedzie lepiej - It will be better, Polish Musical Revue, program, financial report, press releases, clippings, correspondence., April 30, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Za Nasza i Wasza Wolnosc - For our Freedom and Yours, Polish musical show, program, financial report, press releases, clippings., April 6, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Alliance College Kujawiaki, program, posters, clippings., December 17, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Echa Ojczyzny - Echo of Poland, Polish Musical Show, program, press releases, correspondence, financial report., March 33, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Wszystkiego Najlepszego - With Best Wishes, Polish musical show, program, press releases, correspondence, financial report., November 16, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Rzeszowiacy, Polish Folk, Song and Dance Company, program, press releases, correspondence, financial report., April 25, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Polish Textile Artists - Exhibit, catalog, financial report, press releases., October 1, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Sami Swoi - Among Ourselves, program, financial report, press releases., March 28, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Dawnych Wspomnien Czar - Memories of Yesteryear, program, financial report, press release., October 17, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- W Sama Dziesiatke - Right on Target, program, financial report, press release., April 27, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Byle Bylo Tak - Wish it were so, program, press release, financial report, Nov. 26, 1980., November 26, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Podwieczorek przy mikrofonie - Odnawiamy sie, program, press release, financial report., April 1, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Jolanta Brachel and Marek Chwast - piano recital, program, financial report, press release., May 7, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Jubileusz na wesolo - Happy Jubilee, program, press release, financial report., October 27, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Cala sala spiewa - Everyone sings, program, financial report, press release., April 13, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Bedziemy razem - Let's be Together, program, financial report, press release., November 3, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Gdzie te czasy - Where are these days, program, financial report, press release., March 12, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Halka - Polish opera performance, program, financial report, press release., October 19, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Camille A. Budarz piano Recital, program, financial report, press release., October 29, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The Polish Millennium - an essay by Eugene Kusielewicz, vice president of the Kosciuszko Foundation., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sing, Poland, Sing: an anthology of verse on Polish Topics by sister M. Florence Tumasz., undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Selections" from the poetry of Edmond Kowalewski, translation by sister M. Florence Tumasz., undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Dwa serca = Two hearts: an anthology of Polish verse by Sister M. Florence Tumasz., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Her red dress [offprint from Patron] translated from Polish by Sister M. Gloria Czarniewicz and Sister M. Florence Tumasz., undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Sister M. Florence Tumasz, C.S.F.N. - Curriculum Vitae, clippings, correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Rapperswil - pamphlets from the Polish museum., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Poland - pre-WW II pamphlets for tourists., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Poland - after WWII tourist guides, maps. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Poland - various theater programs. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Materials separated. (Box 2, Folder 15)